Silicon Valley royalty. Legendary
investor Bill Gurley.
>> Track record's incredible.
>> The legend who backed Uber and Zillow
who's lived through every major tech
cycle for over 25 years.
>> You're not just a commentator, right?
You've been an operator.
>> I'd love to unlock this latent human
potential. There's been no time in the
history of the world where you can learn
faster. You can increase your surface
area for luck. I'm not a big fan of
these dystopian narrative. The thing to
do right now is to run as fast as you
can. Please welcome Bill Gurley.
It's good to be here again. Three years
ago, I gave a talk on regulatory capture
and this group was uh quite kind and how
they reacted and how that video was
promoted. And I'm very happy we got that
word out into the public discourse.
Obviously today you hear it quite a bit.
Um I have a different topic I'm going to
talk to you about today. It's not I'm
not going to talk about AI. Um it's a
serious topic and so there might not be
as many fun joke parts in it. Um, but
it's something that's been weighing on
my mind for the past five or six years
and I'm thankful that the team here
allowed me to come to talk to you about
it and I'm hopeful that we can have an
impact by getting the word out on this
as well.
I'm going to start by talking to you
about some catastrophes that have
happened in the world and how humans
normally respond to them. This is the
Chamberlain Towers in Surfside, Florida.
You may remember in June of 2021 when
the building suddenly collapsed, 98
people died. What happened? There were
design areas from the very beginning.
There's poor maintenance schedule. And
then the the board of the condominium
did not listen to an inspection report
that said they needed to take care of
this. Three different things. That's
kind of the institutional failure. The
technical failure was different. And you
can see it here. This is a New York
Times article. Hopefully they can push
play so you can see. It's a um it's a 3D
article. If if if they can't make it
play, you'll have to watch it on your
own. Um here we go. But the reason I
want you to see this isn't to talk about
the details of exactly how this
collapsed. It turned out the pool deck
was exposed to saltwater air. It
corroded. The pool deck collapsed into
the basement which took out the
structural columns and the building came
down. But what I want you to take away
from this is the New York Times and its
investigative team had excruciating
detail about how this happened, which
comes from doing primary investigative
work.
There were four other parallel
investigations that happened. The NIST
is the National Institute of Standards
and Technology. After 9/11, they were
assigned as a federal agency to go
investigate what happens in a building
collapse. These two individuals, Matrini
Risner and Bell, would spend five years
on this. Allan Kilshimer is the wolf of
building collapses. He's who you call
when you want to figure out what
happened. The town of Surfside hired
him. Judge Randall would convene a grand
jury in the state of Florida to
investigate this. And there were 17
victim lawsuits which got put under a
single class. Tropin was the the
defender or the litigant and Hodsman was
the judge that did that. All of these
different groups were doing
investigations on their own. Sometimes
running into each other, sometimes
helping each other out, but all trying
to get at what caused the failure.
One particularly heroic group was the
Miami Herald. They had just gone through
bankruptcy. They had a new executive
editor named Monica Richardson, but they
went after this hard. The beat reporter,
Alan Liuititz, was on the scene within
two hours. Sarah Blaski would lead an
investigative team. They would
eventually find Don Leman who's a
professor at the University of
Washington. She would join the team. Um
they would they would staff up to 37
people on this. They have a 3D uh model
that's equally impressive to the New
York Times one and they would deservedly
win a Pulitzer Prize for the work that
they did. Um, when they won it, Monica
Richardson, the executive editor, who
also won an award for executive editor
of the year from her peers, said, "We
will continue to investigate the
collapse to find answers to how this
happened to ensure a tragedy like this
never happens again." Now, finding the
failure cause doesn't help if you don't
prevent. This is a list of some of the
changes that went into all the
condominium rules in Florida. And
thankfully multiple other states,
especially coastal states, adopted them.
So you have change that causes
prevention. That's what you want to have
happen when these things happen. 737 Max
crash. Unfortunately, there were two
crashes, October 2018 and March 2019.
For those of you who don't know know
what happened, let me give you the
really short version. Airbus had come
out with a plane that was incredibly
fuel efficient and they were starting to
take share from Boeing. Boeing wanted to
respond. If they built a new plane, it
required tons of hours of teaching and
training and and that makes it harder to
sell. So, they decided they would attach
a fuel efficient engine to an old plane,
the 737. That's how you get the name 737
Max. The problem is the engine was too
big and they had to move it forward on
the wing. When you move it forward on
the wing, the plane is imbalanced. and
and they had this problem during test
flights when it would occasionally tip
up. So they wrote a piece of software,
secret software called MCAS, MCCast, and
they put it in there without telling
anybody. And if if the sensor went off
and told him the plane was tipping up,
the autopilot would push it down. The
poor pilot that was flying the Ethiopian
Airways flight, his sensor
malfunctioned. the the the software
thought that the plane was tilting up
and it pushed it into the ground. That's
what happened.
There were many people that investigated
this. I call them the six searchers. The
US government did a Senate Commission, a
House Commission, and the DOJ went after
it. KNKT is the Indonesian firm that or
the Indonesian agency that had the right
to inspect the black boxes. They could
tell very quickly the pilot was fighting
the autopilot. The press played a key
role. Dominique Gates had followed
Boeing for the Seattle Times for 16
years. He would win a Pulitzer for his
work here. Peter Robersonson wrote a
book called Flying Blind. You can tell
why it would have that title. 57
whistleblowers sent letters into the
Senate to tell on Boeing. The victim's
family showed up and were ever present
and put pressure on Congress to make
sure something happened. And the uh the
head of the pilot union was very upset
that that they had put this piece of
software in there and not told the
pilots. Boeing tried to come have a sit
down with the pilots union and they
secretly recorded what Boeing said and
gave it to the press. And then when they
wouldn't respond to Boeing's request,
the pilots union issued FOIA request
against Boeing. It's unheard of. Now, in
these situations where you have six
searchers, you also have blockers. And
unfortunately, in this case, both Boeing
and the FAA were being unhelpful in
trying to find out what happened. Boeing
initially accused the pilots of not
being trained well enough.
The FAA refused document requests to the
Senate panel.
And one thing I would tell you about
these big organizations, when you put a
spotlight on them, they can feel the
weight of that spotlight and they circle
the wagons. I think part of it's
institutional. I don't think they're
necessarily evil. They're just they have
a sick sense about how to respond when
they're put on the spot like that. Um
the other thing that's interesting here
is a lot of people came to think that
Boeing and the FAA were working as one.
Um, Senator Ted Cruz when he had the
head of the FAA in front of in front of
the Senate literally accused him of
being captured. There's our favorite
word again. Um, and he even said to him,
"Sir, do you know you don't work for
Boeing?"
Um,
one one of the real failures here in
this case, 45 days after the first
crash, almost everyone knew the MCAST
software was at fault and no one
grounded the plane. Boeing didn't ground
the plane. The FAA didn't ground the
plane. And the second crash, I mean, the
first crash should have never happened
because that piece of software should
have been identified, which would have
required retraining, but the second
crash should have really never happened.
I wanted to share with you, I don't want
to go through this in detail, but these
are the two different committees in the
House and the Senate. And I just want to
highlight that they were decidedly
bipartisan. DeFazio was the head of the
House committee, very active. Ted Cruz
and Wicker were super active. No one
thought this was anything that should be
partisan, nor should it be.
It turns out the scientific community
has a process they use when they want to
do failure analysis. It's called Kappa.
Captive and preventive action. And there
there are five steps. You detect, you
investigate, confirm root cause,
correct, and prevent. And it's all about
prevention. You want to stop this from
happening again. But you can't skip root
cause. That's a that's a requirement.
you don't know how to fix it if you
don't know actually what happened. Um,
CAP is required by law by the FDA and
pharmaceuticals and medical device. The
aerospace industry has regulations that
require this type of process if you have
a failure. Now, let's move on. Hurricane
Katrina 2005.
Um, look at look at these stats. They're
horrible. 1,800 deaths, 400,000 people
displaced, damage $125 billion. What
happened here? Well, the Army Corps of
Engineers that built the levey want you
to believe that the water went over the
levies, but that's, you know, an an act
of God, natural disaster. But this was
only a hurricane or category 3 level
hurricane. What in fact happened was the
levies gave way from underneath. They
washed under. Um, and that's what's
unfortunate is this was a preventable
accident as well. Um, as with these
others, you have searchers and blockers.
The House had a had a commission. The
Senate had a commission. The press
played a key role. Mark Slestein and and
John Mcuade um had written a series
three years earlier about how this could
happen. They would win two Pulitzers. I
actually had a chance to talk with John
about it. Um the NSF, the National
Science Foundation cared so much about
this, they did a bake off for to have
another team doing investigation and
these two professors from the University
of California led that. And then the the
state of Louisiana hired a team out of
LSU and they all investigated and I you
know I talked to John sometimes once
again running into each other sometimes
blocking sometimes sharing notes but and
they all came to the exact same
conclusion that this was a man-made
error. The US core of engineers is the
one that built the levies and they
naturally as I talked about are going to
act as blockers. What's weird here is
they asked the uh American Society of
Civil Engineers if they would um join
the investigation, join the internal
investigation. They paid him a million
dollars. Um and over time they would
just get kind of encapsulated inside the
Army Corps and become blockers
themselves. When this dust all settled,
Raymond Seed, the uh professor from
UKAL, he wrote a 42page report to the
ASCE explaining all the times that they
blocked. That document's on the
internet. You can go see it. Like 42
pages, that's a lot of blocking. Um the
other thing that happened here that's
great is prevention. Um these different
investigations led to 90
recommendations. Those changes were made
and the seaw walls have held it was $15
billion. Seaw walls have held now for 20
years, which is great. Let me move
through a couple more real quickly. This
is Fukushima.
2200 deaths, 154,000 displaced, 200
billion in cleanup. Um, what happened
here is is pretty simple. The seaw wall
in front of the nuclear plant was 5.7 m.
The water went over the wall, took out
the generators, the cores started to
melt down. There was no way to cool
them. and the disaster happened. Um,
there were internal documents that
showed they expected tsunamis in a
30-year window to be in the 10 to 15 m
range and they buried the report. So, if
you had simply raised the wall, this
never happens. But it didn't happen. And
in a lot of these cases, there's a
combination of a technical failure and
an institutional failure. The technical
failure is what happens, you know, to
the product or the surface of the
building or the seaw wall. the
institutional failures. Why did the
humans let that become a weak point
here? Um, as with the others, their
searchers and blockers, the press played
a role. Martin Fler would at the New
York Times spent 20 years in the Tokyo
bureau. He would be a puliter finalist.
Mr. Yorimitsu took a third the third
place paper and added 20 investigators
to his staff to go after this. Had a
huge impact, won two awards. the
Japanese citizens were out in force both
protesting and filing claims. And just
like the FAA and uh Boeing, TCO was the
company running the power plant. Nissa
was the regulator and they blocked and
they and they blocked and they got in
the way. And in fact, the failure was
partially just a result of regulatory
capture once again that they they
weren't playing the right role of
regulator and regul. They had almost
become friends. Now, the real hero of
this story is a guy named Curios
Kurukawa. Um, he was asked by the
Japanese Parliament to lead the first
ever private investigation they've ever
had in their country's history. And they
had they had a lot of power. They they
were told that no one on the committee
could have any institutional connection
to the regulator or the power company.
They had the full authority to go after
anybody in any way. And they had a ton
of meetings. Here are some of the stats.
Kira Cowell, when he kicked this off,
said he had three mandates that he
wanted to adhere to. One, he cared about
human safety. He didn't want it to be a
battle about nuclear energy. Two, he
said the investigation should definitely
result in recommendations.
And third, he knew the weight of this
because of three Mile Island and
Cherobyl from a global perspective, and
he cared about that. Now, interestingly,
he's a medical doctor. He's not a
nuclear physicist, but he led this this
commission with a level of grace and
professionalism that that makes him a
hero from my perspective. All these
searchers are heroes from my
perspective. He would publish a report 7
months later. Interestingly, they chose
to publish it in English first because
they were worried about global
transparency and how they were
perceived. And in the in the first
sentence, he says, "The accident at the
power plant cannot be regarded as a
natural disaster. It was profoundly
man-made, and it could have and should
have been prevented." Powerful.
One last one. This is the uh Challenger
Shuttle disaster. Um January 1986. I
remember where I was. It was a Tuesday.
I was in college. It was a long time
ago. Um, everyone, if you've seen the
documentaries, you know what happened
here. The O-rings on the solid rocket
boosters weren't designed for cold.
Turns out it was cold that morning in
Florida, and that flaw caused a problem.
Unfortunately,
the subcontractor that had worked on
that piece tried to object the night
before that they shouldn't launch and he
got shut down. So, you have a technical
failure and institutional failure once
again. Now, I could talk about a lot of
searches and blockers, but I'm just
going to talk about one, Richard
Fineman, who was already mentioned uh
during the all-in conference this week.
Um, Richard Fineman's a was a professor
at Caltech. Um when when the shuttle
challenger blew up, Ronald Reagan
created the Rogers Commission and they
added mostly insiders, Neil Armstrong,
they had astronauts, they had generals,
they had people from Washington, people
from NA NAS NASA executives, but someone
had the idea that they should put
Fineman on there. And I think they
wanted like a stamp of approval from a
physicist. The good the good news is it
made a lot of sense. He's uh one of the
most famous scientists of all time. He
um won a Nobel Prize and he worked on
the Manhattan project, so he had a lot
of credibility. What they didn't know is
he's fiercely independent. He's highly
truth seeeking and he has zero time for
unnecessary diplomacy. They didn't know
that was coming. Um he didn't want to do
it. He said he hated Washington. I kind
of get that. Um his wife talked him into
it, but once he did it, he cleared his
schedule. He took everything off his
calendar for 6 months into the future.
None of the other commission members did
that and he started doing investigation
on his own before he ever went to
Washington. He's like showing up at NASA
facilities and like asking to meet with
people. And when he got to Washington,
none of the other members wanted to act
that way. In fact, Neil Armstrong told
him, you know, we just evaluate. We
don't investigate. It was too late. He
was already doing it. Now, three fun
facts about this. Um, first of all,
there's a famous story. If you watch any
of the documentaries where Rogers runs
into Neil Armstrong in the bathroom and
says, "Fineman's being a real pain in
the ass." Um, the second thing is he
staged a stunt on live television. He
found some material that was similar to
the O-ring and and in front of
everybody, he dipped it in his cold ice
water in front of him and picked pulled
it out and cracked it to show the
failure. It infuriated the rest of the
commission. And then lastly, when he
submitted all his notes to the
commission, they wrote a final report.
They didn't they really kind of smoothed
over everything and he was pissed. And
so he called Rogers and said, "You know
what? Take my name off of it." Of
course, he'd already done the thing on
TV. There's no way they could take their
name off of it. They caved. Appendix F
to the report is all of his notes
included in their entirety. Now, why am
I talking to you about all these
catastrophes and searchers and blockers
and heroes like Kiraawa and Fineman?
Because I want to talk to you about
COVID 19.
In December of 2019, CO 19 caused 15
million deaths, disrupted every life on
the planet, and cost our globe $45
trillion.
It was particularly hard on children.
You've read about learning loss. My kids
were in high school and college and
missed three years of the most formative
years of your life. I never want to live
through this thing again in my life. But
guess what? For all the
for all the other catastrophes, I told
you what root cause is. 6 years later,
we don't know. So, forgive me if I'm
unafraid of what some AI guy's chatbot
is going to do to humanity when you
can't tell me what this thing already
did.
My my my P second co is way higher than
my pdoom. And if their models are so
smart, tell me what happened here.
Let's get them working on this problem.
I want to I want to put this in
perspective. I've added up all the
deaths and cost of the five catastrophes
I tal walked through with you and you
get to 5,000 deaths and $349 billion. CO
is 3,000 times bigger than that. Fineman
in one of the documentaries said someone
was telling him he needed to be nicer
and he said, "But seven people died." If
if you if you have to get through
nicities and seek truth when seven
people died, how are you supposed to
behave when 15 million people die?
I can take it even further. I add up all
plane accidents, all hurricanes, all
nuclear accidents, all building
collapses, all space accidents. You
still only get one-third of the way to
what happened with CO.
We should want to know what happened
here so we can stop this from happening
again.
Here's what didn't happen. And this is
shocking because all these wonderful
people, all these well-intended people
did this in the other cases which were
much smaller. And they did it in a
purposeful and meaningful way. There's
no committed newsroom with over 30
investigators on CO. None of the major
papers did that. There was no Gates or
Schle Schelestein or Flacker like a a
dogged investigative reporter that had
the backing of his newsroom going after
this. No bipartisan Senate congressional
committees like you had in Katrina and
737 Max. You didn't have a standalone
investigation with someone like Fineman
or or or Kiraawa. Um, there was no
sciencefunded investigation. The the
NIST and the NSF launched them in these
other two cases. NIH didn't fund a
third-party investigation here and no
massive victims lawsuit to figure out
what happened. So, what went wrong? I'm
going to share some thoughts with you
and I I want you to be aware of a couple
piece of information that I think are
kind of new or new to be understood. Um,
but I and I want to make one one
qualification. This has been bothering
me for a long time. I've read a ton. Um,
I I'm sure there are people that are
smarter than me on this, but I'm got to
be top 1% in terms of how much
information I've consumed. The first
thing I would tell you is these five
people were relied on as experts. You
know, the first two, Francis Collins,
Anthony Fouchy, Peter Dazzic runs
something called the Ecoalth Alliance.
It's a nonprofit that did viology
research. Jeremy Ferrar was the head of
the welcome trust that funded a lot of
this stuff and went on to work at the
WHO. And then Ralph Bareric is the top
veriologist in the US at the University
of North Carolina. What I'm here to tell
you is they weren't experts. They were
blockers. They acted exactly like FAA
and Boeing and NASA did in these other
situations. And I'm going to give you
four reasons why I know they're
blockers. First, they're verology
insiders. So, as I said, there's going
to be a natural instinct to circle the
wagon when someone shines a spotlight on
you.
Two, they led a misinformation campaign
to take us off the lead and to tell us
not to search. I'm going to tell you
about that in a second.
Three, they were all outspoken gain of
function advocates prior to CO coming
along. And if you don't know what gain
of function is, is when you take a virus
and you make it intentionally more
dangerous to animals or humans. They
felt that that was smart to do. Obama
had outlawed it. they were constantly
promoting to try and make it more happen
more often. Fauci in 2011 wrote an
article in the Washington Post an
editorial where he said the pros
outweigh the cons. Now, if you talk to
any behavioral psychologist, if you've
told the world, we should definitely do
this and the pros outweigh the cons.
There's zero chance you can be impartial
when it comes to figuring out what
happened. Because to go home at night
and think that something you did
contributed to the death of 15 million
people would be impossible to go to bed.
Your brain's much more likely to trick
you into just thinking it didn't happen.
You wouldn't be allowed on a jury if you
had that kind of of bias. And the fourth
reason, and the most important reason I
know they're blockers, is because they
didn't search. I tell you they stopped
searching but they never started
searching and they should have been
searching. They should still be
searching.
There are people that did search.
They're not at large institutions. The
two on the bottom drastic is a loosely
affiliated group of scientists that come
together and share information. They
have a website. You should follow them.
Um it's like 20 Nick Shirley's that are
all veriologists or scientists. Um, US
right to know is a nonprofit that's
filed the majority of the FOIA claims
here. And um, you can donate to them. I
have. But I want to tell you about these
five heroes. They're heroes of mine that
have been actively trying to find out
what happened from the very beginning.
Alina Chan was one of the first
molecular biologists that that realized
that the virus looks like it was
designed for humans. She wrote a book
with Matt Ridley. And here's some really
good news. In the past couple of years,
the New York Times has published two of
her op-eds. I would rather it be the
investigative team at the New York
Times, but it's a start. They're really
good. Read both of them. Katherine Ebon
was the first person to really stick
their neck out and say, "We're not
looking at this the right way." She
published an article, oddly in Vanity
Fair, titled The Fight to Discover COVID
Origins. And I I think the title is
important because the fight was about
the discovery process.
Emily Cop worked for us right to know.
She may know more than anybody. She's
been the one uncovering all of these
documents and we've been getting more
and more documents each and every day.
So, we're learning more. Zade Tufeki is
a professor at Princeton who also writes
sometimes for the New York Times. I'm
going to tell you something she did
recently that I think is super
important. And then Allison Young wrote
a book called Pandora's Gamble that
looks at all of the lab leak failures
that have happened prior to CO which is
an interesting and relevant data point
to study if you want to consider whether
or not that was part of the problem.
These five women have been attacked for
sticking their neck out. Some of them
directly by the men on the previous
slide. And I think that's completely
unreasonable.
Um I think they're heroes.
Now, there's two things I want to tell
you about and then I'll and then I'll
I'll wrap it up. There's two pieces of
information you should know about. I
said earlier that the five
experts/blockers
had had created a misinformation
campaign to take us off the lead. I
think that's an understatement on what
they created a highly successful
misinformation campaign to convince
everyone that lab that animal spillover
was a decidedly
determined uh cause of this and that
anyone that considered a lab leak even
thought about it or asked a single
question was a conspiracy theorist and
they were successful at it. They
leveraged the the scientific journal
community which they understood. The
proximal origins paper went out like
this thing was written in like a week.
There's no way you did an investigation.
They just wanted to to to get it out
there and then the Lancet had a similar
one. The these these papers have been
cited over and over over again. If you
try and like go through Wikipedia, you
just always end up going back to them.
So they were highly successful. They
also somehow made this thing partisan.
using the word conspiracy theory with
Trump back. I don't know how it
happened, but they were able to get
people in their surveys and polls,
people, what do you think caused COVID?
And if you're Democrat or Republican,
you have a different answer. That's
nuts. Like there's no way that should be
relevant in this discussion. um recently
more and more of this information's come
out and so you have um more more
understanding of how they came to write
these papers like and you can see
inconsistencies between what they think
and what they wrote. Um Zayep put this
on Twitter 45 days ago and I think she
chose her words very carefully. She
said, "Incont
incontrovertible proof of a conspiracy
to cover up and deny the possibility it
well may be a lab mishap orchestrated
from the highest levels of the
scientific establishment and a
self-serving group of scientists who
deliberat deliberately misled the
public." Those are strong words. She put
that up 45 days ago. It has 400,000
views and zero community notes. At least
today. Maybe tomorrow we'll have some.
Um Katherine Ebon w was more tur but
equally opinionated. She calls it
manufactured consensus. If you feel
strongly you think you know what
happened in CO you need to understand
that this happened. It took people off
the scent. Three years after CO the
drastic team uncovered this document.
It's called the diffuse proposal. Who's
heard of the diffuse proposal? Raise
your hand. This is nuts. Look it's like
three people. Okay. Um, no major
journals ever covered the diffuse
proposal. It's um, there was a survey of
scientists who who they said, "Do you
what do you think caused it?" If they
said animal spillover, they said, "Have
you heard of diffuse?" Only 70 only 22%
had. 78% said they had never heard of
it. What's the diffuse proposal? Three
years after CO drastic uncovered this
document. You can go download it. It's
real. Um, it was a proposal by Ecoalth
Alliance, Peter Dazzic's company to that
connects the top veriologist at Duke in
North Carolina with the top veriologist
at Wuhan, the the bat lady, Jun Lee. And
there's a proposal that they're going to
insert a fern cleavage site at the S1S2
junction of a bat corona virus because
they think it'll make it more viral in
animals. and it's in a document.
I went to AI. I said, "Let's do a clean
session AI." That means don't look at
anything I've ever told you before. If I
were interested in helping to solve the
origin of CO and I was using the
scientific principles of Kappa to guide
me, how would I react to finding the
diffuse proposal? Look at these answers.
Direct investigational lead, highly
critical, major investigative lead. Yes,
that would be a high priority piece of
evidence. primary document evidence,
highest tier evidence class. Most people
don't know about this thing. And I I
would make an assertion. Had this
document been exposed in January of
2020, we would have had a very different
conversation back then. Um but it
wasn't. The searchers are aware of the
document. Rand Paul's aware of the
document. Hopefully now you're all aware
of the document. One other thing I I I
think I need to say, um, if you ask
these AI bots, what would you do next in
your cappa profit process, they say you
would go after documents at Duke
University and University of North
Carolina. And the searchers have been
doing that. Unfortunately, the
University of North Carolina and the
state of North Carolina are blockers.
They're refusing to deliver the
documents. And I would encourage if any
of you have connections to UNCC or know
anyone on the board, I would encourage
you to make them think about whatever
they're protecting and whether that's
more important than preventing the next
one of these.
Um, if you want to learn more about
this, Matt Ridley just did an interview
last March with Jay Bacharia at NIH.
It's a great way to catch up on
everything people have been learning.
And as we look forward, and this is
where I'd love your help, let's support
the searchers. We have to find a root
cause to this thing. We don't want this
to happen again. Um,
I can't tell you that I speak for
science like Anthony Fouchy did, but I
can tell you I speak for scientific
inquiry. There's no one that should be
telling you you can't search. That makes
no sense whatsoever. You're not a bad
person if you search. You're a good
person if you search. Um, you have to
move through and around the blockers. I
don't think you want to attack the
blockers. I think Rand Paul's making a
mistake making it about prosecution. We
should make it about root cause and
prevention. Um, this isn't partisan and
should have never been. If you're view
on what caused COVID is because of who
you vote for, please reconsider that.
Um, I would ask the newsrooms to dive
in, be like Monica Richardson, and then
let's put a truly independent commission
together. Let's find our cure cower or
fineman. I'm going to leave you with a
quote. I'm way over time. I'm going to
leave you with a quote that's attributed
to Plato that sums up what I've been
thinking here.
We can easily forgive a child who is
afraid of the dark. The real tragedy in
life is when men are afraid of the
light. Thank you.
Wow. I got to ask a question. Stay out
here. No. No. Stay out here. Stay out
here. Can I do a question?
>> Another standing ovation here. Um,
Bill, wow. Uh, you put a tremendous
amount of effort into this. Uh, we've
known each other for 30 years. I've seen
you emotional, I think, two other times.
One was a Jason Esbell concert.
Another time you you you your your top
set got counterfeited or something. But
this is emotional and this is personal
for you. what they did to our kids is
really clearly impacted you. Maybe you
could talk about why it's so important
that we consider the damage that was
done to this generation.
>> Well, I mean, for me, it's all back to
prevention. Like, like you have to stop
it from happening again. I have zero
confidence right now that if another
pandemic started tomorrow, we'd have any
better way to navigate it. I think we
might do worse
>> because of the the misinformation
campaigns cause a lack of trust. Next
time you're not going to listen to them.
There's not going to be ability for
anybody to lead. And I'm I'm struck, as
you can tell by the presentation, by the
difference between the the attitude of
the people that searched in these other
catastrophes, how they were viewed as
heroes, and what happened to the people
that were looking here.
>> Yes. And it it you repeatedly talk about
the power of journalism, Pulitzers and
investigative journalism specifically
which is different than clickbait
journalism. There is something very
virtuous about investigative journalism
and those type of journals. Maybe you
could speak to that and then explain to
us why people didn't go after the
Pulitzer here, why they didn't put a
large amount of resources to because
that seems incredibly suspicious. And I
I seem to have a recollection of Fouchi
getting a pardon, which also seems to be
a red flag that you didn't bring up. So
take those two issues.
>> Well, yeah. So on the investigative
part, I mean, one of the reasons I
mentioned all the pulters was just to
highlight that fact, right? Um there's a
wonderful video on YouTube, if you're
interested in this topic at the
Brookings Institute, three or four of
the of the ladies that I showed led a
panel to talk about why the press missed
this. And both Katherine and Emily Cop
pointed back to the mis the
misinformation campaign by the verology
experts and how they kind of made it
like a faux paw to actually ask
questions which but it considering the
scale of the outcome is just horrible
that that happened and
>> and I would once again I would encourage
them like there's still work to do.
There's still information coming out.
We're getting closer. Like come on in.
>> Yeah. And there's something really
tragic here in that if you asked
questions this time, you were put into a
conspiracy theorist who didn't trust the
uh experts and you were the damage.
>> Yeah.
>> For asking questions. This is pure evil.
>> It's crazy.
>> I mean, it's pure evil to take the
people who just say, "Hey, is it
possible this came out of the Wuhan?
guys have if you you in fact funded gain
of research. Why is that such a hard
question for them to answer? It's
>> Well, I said I I I think a behavioral
psychologist would tell you you you
you're able to fool yourself to keep
your own sanity.
>> Yeah. Now, I'll just end with this.
Knowing what you've known, you've put
thousands of hours into this. You and I
have been talking about this for three
or four years now. and and this has been
a passion project of yours and I really
appreciate you sharing it with the
audience. What do you believe
based on what you know now is the most
likely scenario of how CO originated and
and what we can learn from it just based
on you being in the
>> I would tell you I intentionally didn't
take a side on that here and cuz cuz we
haven't found root cause and I would
>> celebrate you know anyone that that's
100% convinced it's animal spillover to
do research there I funded US right to
know if you want to go search for the
animals. I'll fund that, too. You should
know China has tested 80,000 animals and
not found a single crossover. A and
they're they have a huge incentive to
find one if they could.
>> Yes. The wet market theory would be
absolutely free them from having
fingerprints
>> and and right. So, so there's a massive
incentive. Why hasn't But but if you
want to keep looking, go look. Fouchi in
these documents that have been uncovered
admitted there were multiple cases prior
to the spreader event at the wet market
which also is another problem you have
to deal with.
>> Yeah. Uh listen, Bill, I think this
could wind up being the uh most
important work of your life and as your
friend I'm I'm just in awe of your
passion and your doggedness and any way
we can support it. I I think everybody
here and in the audience at Allin would
love to donate to more research being
done. So So we'll tweet that in the
future. Let's give it up one more time
for Bill Gurley.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, brother. You crush it.